you
welcome to the next mobility podcast on
this week's episode we have the founder
and CEO of comedy I George ha George
Hotz welcome to the podcast George hi
yeah so I thought to really kind of dive
into some of the details on on some of
the autonomous technology that you guys
are developing we'd start by kind of
tackling the reason why you started this
company and you know why you didn't kind
of jump along you know say Google
Google's whammo project or uber or Tesla
and that sort of thing so what do you
what's kind of your main reason for
starting common data AI because do you
really want to live in a world
controlled by way more oh that's a great
question yeah
it seems it seems as though they're kind
of pursuing something quite different
than say they did with Google's even
their own search engine or what they've
done with Android of course which at
which I know you've been quite vocal
about and so you know how are you guys
approaching it from a different angle
than some of those bigger companies
developing this technology well I mean
it's not just a question of you know a
different angle it's a question of who's
gonna win and who's gonna lose
wham-o and Google I'm sorry way mo and
uber operate in bubbles um they operate
in enclosed bubbles where they think
that they can control the entire stack
of mobility no and he'll mm-hmm and so
you see it kind of being a multiple
company operation in terms of someone's
getting the ride shares called someone's
operating the autonomous technology and
you know some other company might
maintain the vehicles and that sort of
thing forget about it this is the kind
of people who spend their day like
jerking off about the future no
seriously though they spent like oh the
world is gonna transform in ten years
now right now people buy cars and they
crash right how do you make them buy
cars that don't crash i Tesla's got this
right so instead of you know tackling it
you know with some like you said some
kind of futuristic mindset you you're
kind of approaching it from you know how
can we improve the safety and how can we
move it where people will accept it you
know a lot faster rather but how do you
win right yeah how do you how you win
seven cars and I said this since the
beginning right the way Moe an uber
approach doesn't win
I mean uber has more of a shot of that
than way Moe look at Google Fiber right
it's a great ISP how many places have it
- yeah yeah right
it was a little burr fiber all right
maybe maybe they'd be able to roll out
the the ISP but kudou be really handled
the technological challenges no it's
just not the way the world is gonna play
out the world's gonna play out a whole
lot more like what you've seen in the
smartphone industry right I mean this
happened before in computing this idea
of thin clients this is all you can you
can trace this back 40 years like this I
did Oh everyone's just gonna own a thin
client
we're not even all in the thin climb
maybe it'll just rent the thin client
from the other leg everyone will have
Bloomberg terminals I mean this isn't
how computing happened right mm-hmm and
so when you're looking at developing
internally it come a you know your cars
are they still using lidar like uber and
and way moe
or are you moving towards the more
computer vision aspect of development
well I mean that's a technology choice
I'm not sure why the reason people
fixated on lidar is because way moe does
have a technological lead and because
they use lidar if the year is 2005 and
you just witnessed
everybody lose miserably at the DARPA
Grand Challenge in 2004 lighter gets
invented people start winning in 2005
lighter looks like a great idea fast
forward you know almost 15 years
computer vision is amazing the AI
revolution is happening computer vision
is superhuman in some categories and
cameras have this two huge advantages
they're cheap and they're passive right
you don't want a sensor on your car that
has to actively emit stuff
this isn't how humans drive right humans
drive by humans don't have any active
sensors there's like that's bats too but
like um no humans don't have active
sensors right you don't want active
sensors active sensors interfere with
each other on the they're more likely to
you know be thrown by their own
interference because you have both a
transmit and a received pathway and
lidar is ridiculously expensive and so
yeah I've talked about that with some of
some executives in the you know kind of
evie space or autonomy space and they've
they've always said that they've they've
always you know
kind of emphasized oh well lidar works
really well except for the fact that
it's very difficult to manufacture and
it cost a crazy amount of money it's
also like it doesn't work well here's
the thing right when you think about the
the problems involved in self-driving
cars there's like a perception problem
and then there's a planning problem
right the lidar only helps you with the
perception part of that problem
maybe there's perception planning and
localization sure the lighter might help
you with perception localization but
when it comes to planning we're really
all the hard problems lie it doesn't
matter right like that's we are much
better at like object classification
detection and recognition and computer
vision than we are at like complicated
decision-making required for actually
driving cars um it's just it's just such
a trivial part of the problem it's like
we were playing Monopoly and the first
thing I focused on was well you know you
have to build your houses evenly on the
property you can't put three houses
there in one house that's irrelevant
right mm-hmm and and so when you're
talking about computer vision technology
and how much it's advanced in the past
you know 10 15 years where do you think
we are on kind of the road map to
computer vision you know being advanced
enough to handle you know commercialize
self-driving vehicles it already is you
think it already it's at the level where
it's gonna recognize it enough stuff and
provide enough input into the the AI
develop software and kind of control the
vehicle and a you know advanced
commercialized level yeah I'm telling
you if all I had was the AI technology
today for vision I can we have a demo on
our Twitter where we we use a segment
and a depth that we basically output a
lidar we output a point cloud of the
world around us a segmented point cloud
which is even better we know which the
objects are right that's the easy part
the hard part is okay I'm trying to
merge up here
what's my model for how that person's
going to be hey of assuming the bad
person stepping on the brakes and being
able to represent all of that predictive
complexity particularly predictive
complexity where there's search right
and you have to search when you can take
actions okay if I move my car to the
left here what will the other cars do
being able to reason like that in terms
of counterfactuals AI is really bad at
still
and so what do you think needs to take
place and in terms of AI development to
get it to that level I mean you're
starting to see you're certainly just
looking look at alphago look it look
what just happened
alphago zero like reinforcement learning
works if you have access to a really
powerful simulator the question is where
do you get a really powerful simulator
for for self-driving now you could try
to code your own simulator but you're
running into the hand coding problem
again just in terms of graphics and not
vision right you're coding the graphics
part not the vision part umm yeah and
you're Simula is probably gonna be
pretty restrictive so what you want to
do is you either want to learn a
simulator or you want to use the world
as your simulator and figure out how to
do that safely and so when you're
talking about using computer vision and
in combination with AI on this level for
self-driving vehicles you know there's
not a lot of vehicle or not a lot of
companies kind of pursuing that model
but one of the only other ones out there
is of course Tesla's autopilot and it
seems like the development there has
been a little bit bumpy over at least
the past year and a half or so with you
know Chris Lautner leaving earlier this
year and the be whole sterling Anderson
issue unfolding earlier this year in
past last year
what do you think are some of the
challenges that that Tesla's facing to
bringing some of these features and
developing AI to a level of where they
can bring that full self-driving
technology to the vehicles he only has
an idea in his head he has an ideas head
that it should be easy and he's right it
absolutely should be easy so every time
someone doesn't make it seem easy he
fires them which is actually probably a
good strategy so what's the problem I
mean it's just actually implementing all
the stuff mean implementation is hard
mm-hmm no it's not it's not it's not the
theory the theory is like all there and
so when do you think you know Tesla's
gonna be able to where Elon is gonna be
able to assemble that you know the right
team and all the right pieces to make it
all happen do you think they're getting
close to that or oh one day one day you
know someone a little bit smart is gonna
get become in charge of a car company
and they're gonna be like holy crap or
five years behind Tesla we got to catch
up
all right the Paul Graham is a great
tweet when the iPhone came out all the
phone manufacturers
like wow we're 5 years behind we got to
catch up but when the Model S came out
the car manufacturers have still have no
idea how far they are behind the Model S
has sophisticated compute has OTA has
Linux boxes has a you know a large
touchscreen a modern user interface what
is the Chevy Volt half-right when you
look at it from a very superficial
features base level the Chevy Volt in
the model 3 of the same car when you
look at it from a well I mean consumers
aren't stupid
how many Chevy bolts were sold model
threes you want to buy a model 3 today
it's gonna cost you $100,000 that's how
high the demand is and so good good luck
for cooping what you paid for a Chevy
Volt yeah yeah and and in terms of that
brings us to a really great point do you
think like legacy automakers are really
making any of the right moves to develop
their own self-driving technology or do
you think they're kind of approaching it
in a kind of backwards way I mean you
could buy new Tata me for 450 million
dollars and kicked a can down the road
another five years look a lot of them
are really bad um
cruises are right cruise if you want to
if you want to believe in the way mo
uber world's we're like one company's
gonna own the vertical ya cruises are
right at bat as far as playing the
vertical goes when you look at people
playing the horizontal check out check
out like AI motive they're doing a
pretty good job and in you when you're
talking about playing the whole vertical
to help our listeners understand you
you've previously kind of said that the
Tesla's currently on the path to kind of
be the apple of electric and
self-driving vehicles by you know owning
owning all of the technology from tough
to bottom and really kind of vertically
integrating everything there's a huge
difference
Tesla's not gonna own the fleets Tesla's
figured out how to monetize on the way
to owning the vertical and this is what
Apple does as well Google and uber have
figured out how to sync billions of
dollars on the way to hypothetically
maybe owning a vertical yeah it seems it
seems like once Elon will be able to
turn the fleet into you know a
self-driving fleet of you know
ride-sharing cars you know he's not
gonna own them but Tesla's going to have
a piece of it and they're gonna own all
the technology behind it so it's
like they are kind of approaching it in
a more economically feasible way than
you know
uber with you know trying to buy tens of
thousands of cars and that sort of thing
you know we're doing the exact same
thing you know we're gonna be there with
you with the witty open competitor to
Tesla's Apple right that's the simplest
way to describe it right if you think
that that's the way the world is gonna
shake up if you're a believer in the way
my uber crews world okay I mean that's a
matter of taste if you're a believer in
the in the Ford Toyota Honda I don't
even know what world you live in
I don't know it's a different planet
mm-hmm and so when you're talking about
being the the open source kind of the
the Android of the the world in terms of
comparing it to smartphones you know how
do you get there from where you guys are
right now and how is that kind of
changed over the last couple years so we
have open-source self-driving software
it's it's it's it's neck-and-neck with
autopilot less you know less probably
because we're doing a particularly bad
job and because we're doing a
particularly good job and more probably
because autopilot hasn't been doing a
great job for the last year so it's it's
it's neck-and-neck you can download it
right now install it on on certain
hardware you know we do we sell
compatible hardware we sell it as a
dashcam we don't sell any self-driving
stuff we do sells hardware that is
compatible with open pilot and you can
put it on your supported Honda and
hopefully by the end of this week you're
supported Toyota and with Honda's and
Toyota's that's gonna be six of the top
10 cars sold in America and so you know
win-win will those dash cams and all
that hardware and in software all those
pieces come together where you guys will
be able to sell that as a you know
whether it's directly through the
manufacturer or just off the shelf or
some why should we why should we and so
what's the what's the business model
there oh well I mean there's a lot money
is trivial to get these days look new
tana me just got bought for four hundred
and fifty million dollars they stuck six
lied ours are they stuck they've got six
cars they stuck lighters on them
they got 50 people in a room and they
kind of made the car drive slow around
some unoccupied streets right um there's
so much capital in the world right
mm-hmm it's a question about whoever can
actually build and deliver the
technology we'll never be short on money
mm-hmm so what's the what's the business
model there's a ton of ways to do it the
business model I kind of like is a
subscription-based service okay um you
charge people you know $20 a month to
get your car on the self-driving Network
or you can have limited self-driving
features for free all right once you
want the fancy like point-to-point
navigation stuff that requires the cloud
you have to pay about 20 $30 a month a
reasonable fee um that that's probably
our preferred path to monetization and
so you don't go ahead we don't even have
to sell devices directly to consumers
for that to succeed we just need to get
people running our software I don't care
how people are running it whether you're
running it cuz you got it through a
dealer through your to an OEM by
downloading it from our github you know
it's just it's just a potential customer
mm-hmm and in one one of the players
we've kind of been not talking about but
some of these newcomers in the
automotive space and as you've said you
know if you present the right technology
in the right way it seems like the
capital kind of follows follows along
but what do you think about some of
these other newcomers say something like
Rivia n-- or lucid motors or neo you
know and what are those guys oh you're
talking about the Chinese companies that
think they're gonna make cars in terms
of you know how do you think they play
in the environment and especially in the
self-driving environment you know to be
fair Eevee's are a lot easier to make
today when you look around you look
around say look like SpaceX and Tesla
right when you look around at SpaceX
like there's nothing really
fundamentally that makes rockets that
much easier to build today then they
even were to build in like you know a
long time ago even like the 60s or the
70s right okay you have fancy or
guidance computers maybe you can do your
your recoveries and your nice landings
but when you look at electric cars oh
it's so easy today
Oh a kid could build an electric car in
a garage you buy a pre-manufactured
battery pack a pre-manufactured powerful
motor power and pull inverter and boom
you've built an electric car um so is it
possible for these companies to succeed
yeah maybe
and so kind of back to when you got kind
of started and interested in doing
self-driving cars you you said that Elon
Musk kind of approached you to possibly
run the auto pilot division how did that
kind of shake out and did you have any
interest of joining Tesla well I was
supposed to be a contract I'm supposed
to be a contract I was supposed to be in
and out of this game in a year
mm-hmm but you know I'm stubborn I don't
like to lose so I'll be here a long time
and so you know do you think that AI
development is kind of reaching some of
these levels that that will pose a
threat as kind of Elon Musk kind of been
talking about oh here's the thing about
any weapon right mm-hmm
every weapon that's ever been created
guns don't kill people people kill
people
nuclear bombs don't kill people people
kill people uh it's gonna be the exact
same thing with AI right this idea that
AI presents any like unique challenges
that haven't existed already for every
weapon in history that I'm not sure I
believe but once these powerful agencies
get their hand on AI well you know
nuclear bombs aren't very useful
tactically AI is so that's what you got
to watch out for way more than like a
runaway a eye control problem kind of
sci-fi stuff so you think it's more of
you know whoever's kind of in control of
it which is sort of what Elon Musk was
been saying but in the same sense he's
also been more in general that AI could
kind of start running loose if someone
isn't well I mean we we really shouldn't
conflate those two things I mean think
about Google right Google is the Google
makes all their money from advertising
right what happens when advertising
becomes too good there's a great book
Infinite Jest that goes into this right
what happens when Google starts applying
superhuman AI to matching ads with
people I mean are people anything more
than slaves at that point you see that's
a whole lot scarier than oh we're gonna
be turned into paper clips sure maybe
but uh I don't know I think it actually
we rather the paper clips when it comes
down to it all right so we're gonna
we're gonna take a quick break and then
we'll come right back and kind of talk
about some of your recent products and
how they're kind of assembling a
complete eCos
system for for a self-driving car as we
talk about the future of mobility it's
hard not to ignore Tesla's Model 3 a car
that could potentially disrupt the
entire automotive industry right now
Tesla has been having issues with
scaling up production of the vehicle but
the team
Tesla rowdy has learned this week that
Tesla may put the production back on
track you can check out their coverage
right now and Tesla rowdy calm all right
we're back on the next mobility podcast
with George Hotz the CEO and founder of
Comet III and we're gonna talk a little
bit about their products that they just
released last week with their revamped
website you guys now have a dash cam and
then what you're calling a giraffe
connector within the vehicle and a panda
connector that goes on to the obd2 port
which is in virtually all modern
vehicles can you tell us a little bit
about those those building blocks and
what they mean for comedy III yeah so I
mean like forgetting about really what
they are as products you have to think
about them as Universal building blocks
right um so what the Panda is and
they're dried in the tagline the Panda
is the best universal car interface ever
if you want to interface modern
computers to cars cars have these weird
ports and these weird buses they have
obd ports and cam buses and and and and
weird stuff that computers don't have
computers have USB ports and Wi-Fi
phones and computers to the exact same
thing USB points and Wi-Fi so yeah we
need we need an adapter we need an
adapter that transfers from the kind of
you know buses your car has to the kind
of buses your computer has step 1 build
a good interface and that's that's panda
now then the new product eon is is okay
so now that we have a good interface
between cars and computers we need to
get a computer in your car mm-hmm so you
know I could sell you a big desktop and
you have to put it in the trunk with
your inverter and no one's gonna do that
or how else can I get powerful computers
into cars well that's what he owned is
that it's a smartphone in case I really
but um it's also a powerful computer and
it has a
you know very powerful sensor it has a
camera smartphone cameras are just so
phenomenal with how good they become in
the last couple of years so it's it's a
camera it's a GPS its gyro it's an
accelerometer
you know phones have a lot of the same
senses as people it's got a microphone
it's super powerful sensor and compute
array that you can mount right up on
your dashboard you can connect it up to
your pandas and now you have powerful
compute and a powerful bridge between
the compute and your car and giraffe is
just not everything's accessible very
easily over the OBD connector there's
other hidden buses in your car like
hidden cam buses giraffe just lets you
connect panda to your hidden cam buses
okay and and how do these all interface
with you guys's chauffeur app and and
how does that compare to these so
shippers is software and it runs it's
it's - Bank software but it's it's dash
cam with extra stuff like eventually
we're gonna start to offer forward
collision warnings Lane Departure
warnings maybe even self-driving you
know all that stuff right it's all part
of the same kind of spectrum ranging
from just logging to to literally I type
in where I want to go and my car takes
me there level four right it's all on a
spectrum but in order to make this stuff
possible in order to like be able to
move up along that spectrum we need core
building blocks in your car now Tesla
and like I said
Tesla's five years ahead of every car
manufacturer because if I wanted to
install open pilot or I wanted to
install ship or plus on a Tesla it would
only be a software change because Tesla
has provided the hardware and the
sensors that I need no other car
manufacturer has so we have to build our
own and when you're talking about
Tesla's hardware and the software kind
of coming together one of the the kind
of criticisms or worries about the Model
S and and all their vehicles now is do
you think that all the hardware that
that Tesla has installed in those
vehicles is going to be necessary - or
is going to bring the car all the way to
self driving it'll do exactly what I
promised which is yeah make it drive
twice as safe as a human I had totally
absolutely it's just a software problem
and in terms of
you know the hardware that you guys are
gonna be offering in the future you know
are you guys gonna be offering full
self-driving Hardware on the vehicle
multiple cameras and that sort of thing
so that someone can you know say get a
box in the mail and install it on their
vehicle and that sort of thing so we'll
be offering more and more powerful
computers better and better sensors and
more and more sophisticated interfaces
as time goes on so we can see you know
kind of like you said collision warning
that sort of thing I'm and the current
stuff and then eventually you know
you'll provide a version 2.0 and that
sort of thing yeah maybe we can even go
beyond collision warning right now if
you download our open source software
open Pi that you'll get industry's best
adaptive cruise control and Lane keep
assist it so someone can install that
right now with with your product and you
know well the product doesn't come with
it I'm we don't we don't really
encourage that but if you want to do it
we're not gonna stop you sure sure you
know what one day one day maybe the
product will come with it one day one
day the product will come with it and at
that point you know you're doing
everything to manufacture intends for
for for regulatory and liability reasons
you know if you do this you're on your
own also a bit for quality management
reasons right like like we can provide a
really quality dashcam our self-driving
software's it's cutting-edge yeah yeah
and that's a great segue into kind of
the regulatory issue here you know what
kind of regulatory hurdles do you think
are facing autonomous vehicles and are
we on kind of the right path anyone who
thinks there's actually regulatory
hurdles again is someone who desperately
wants to remain employed kind of doing
nothing um it would be so immoral and
unethical if there was good self-driving
technology in the world for regulators
to try to block it I mean they're
literally sentencing hundreds of people
every day to die if the technology
existed self-driving is entirely a
technology problem if the technology
existed and it was cheap and shippable
it would already be deployed everywhere
no regular no sane regulator would try
to stop it so you think that that you
know most of the time when someone comes
out with new software or new
self-driving things it's at least going
to be an improvement in safety so it'd
be kind of silly for
leaders to hinder that development yeah
okay
did you be honest the reason humans
crash cars is it's just like it's it's
some of them are so bad like people
crash because they're they're drunk
they're distracted they're asleep it's
just like so simple to fix they just
drive their car off the road why should
your car allow you to do that it
shouldn't I mean it's so kind of kind of
looking at the whole big picture hang
here when do you think we're gonna start
seeing these cars completely self Drive
on the road you know level four autonomy
and kind of be in regular people's
driveways I don't know
I don't speculate much in the future
what we'll see I'll say that like way mo
will probably get the first one working
the first one that's actually better
than a human and way mo will ship maybe
200 of them then Tesla will probably be
be second and will be third but you know
it's gonna be like like Xerox PARC the
Macintosh and Windows right I'm so Xerox
PARC had all of his great stuff first
right and where the Xerox PARC stood a
well they're all sitting in the bottom
of a landfill you can actually see a
Google car if you want at the Computer
History Museum it's interesting that
it's already history um so that's
what'll happen that's what'll happen to
way more on Google though ship a few and
eventually line up in landfills
um Tesla will come out first but you
know it'll be like the Macintosh right
it'll be this this high-end piece of
hardware which sure it has all the
future of gooeys and stuff but you know
okay a bunch of people are gonna buy and
it's gonna be cool and you'll get a bit
of a cult around it what you already see
around Tesla and you know will be the
windows will be the Android will be
everywhere even if we thought and in
terms of you know you brought up a great
point there with with Google's way mo
you know they've been around for for
nearly a decade or more at least in the
conceptual phase why do you think it's
taken them so long to get to where they
are and it seems like you know because
because they're Xerox PARC the reason
Xerox never shipped the great computers
great technology built at Xerox PARC but
Xerox made money off copiers alright why
would anyone want this stuff right
Google is a little bit better but
fundamentally they make all their money
off ads yeah like ads are to Google
whatwhat copiers were to Xerox and of
course they're not gonna be they're not
gonna be truly ambitious they're not
gonna be hungry no
there is hungry what are you hungry for
yeah we already make a great living off
copiers yeah right
so it seems yeah you know they're tied
down to their existing business so they
it's kind of hard to see why they should
be taking such big risks and putting a
lot of resources into something that's
arguably completely unrelated yeah and
in terms of what we can expect you know
coming soon from comment that I I
anything you can share on that front
yeah I mean we have our we have our
product line up there now it's it's
about it's about you know supporting
that that's gonna be our product line
for the next year and that hardware is
quite capable um that VAT hardware that
the Panda and the Eon and the giraffes
together is a very capable hardware
system I'd even say that it's it's it's
it's more capable than autopilot one
it's not more capable than autopilot to
you'll have to wait for commas next
product for that but at least the
autopilot that was in like autopilot
when it originally launched we're
launching something that's better than
that and you can do that already with
our hardware it's just a question of
software and of course all our stuff has
full OTA capability so we can t a and
you'll continue to get updates and it'll
get better and better better and and you
guys are open-source software and in all
that development why do i go with the
open-source route with that kind of
development rather than you know white
listening into different companies and
that sort of thing oh god then after
what i have to hire a business
development to you i have to deal with
their business that's not worth it it's
not worth it I'm gonna beat you because
I want to beat you not because I want to
like Oh square away my hundred million
dollars I want to win mmm you'll see
nearly enough of this today in Silicon
Valley you know the technology used to
be cool right like this the stuff oil
used to be cool and then like you know a
bunch of people are like whoa well we
could get rich and not bringing that
thought out all the hangar honors and
that brought out all the people who just
like well well stick lidar on six cars
will will make a deployment in Singapore
no one's ever been to Singapore I'll
never actually see the deployment and
then uh yeah we'll get like 50 people
our room and we'll sell to Delfy for 250
million dollars when we flatter their
their egos about detecting reindeer and
stuff um yeah but no like that's that's
one that's one type of person I'm not
the type of person I want to win and if
I don't win I don't
win but at least that's what I'm trying
to do well yeah there you have it you
know it you know if you're out there to
win rather than in and to give a little
bit of context you you're probably in
the same agreement with with Elon Musk
because you know today he he tweeted
they just on the announcement of Delfy
by and metonymy he just tweeted groan so
hilarious I'm sure I'm sure he totally
agrees with you on that front and it
will be incredibly interesting to watch
this kind of development shakeout over
the next couple years as we get closer
and closer yeah absolutely
thanks so much for joining me on the
podcast today cool thank you Tom
yeah thanks so much thanks for listening
to this episode of next mobility please
subscribe on whatever platform you
listen to podcasts on and if you enjoyed
this episode please leave us a review
problem cover art by Sidney E in
original music by Jack mewho see you
next time
you